<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sayan Maity | Rationally Misbehaved</title>
    <link>/author/sayan-maity/</link>
      <atom:link href="/author/sayan-maity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Sayan Maity</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Sayan Maity</title>
      <link>/author/sayan-maity/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Err..</title>
      <link>/post/err-in/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/err-in/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the previous post we discussed about a model -
$$D= a-bP+u$$&lt;br&gt;
Here, we want to explain how the demand of certain goods changes with the price of that good. But there can be other factors which are affecting the demand for that good. If we go back to our energy drink example, Energy drink is popular in a certain age group. So, if that age group is missing from the area, demand for energy drink will be lower even if the price is same. In many cases these types of factors are unknown to us. We represent all such unknown factors with this $u$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without the presence of these other factors, this relation would be deterministic. In that case if $P$ increased by one dollar, $D$ will decrease by $b$ unit. We can write this as. 
$$\frac{dD}{dP}=-b$$ 
Where, demand is changing with the price when other things are not changing. But in reality,  many things are changing at the same time. So, if the price $P$ increased by one dollar, that does not necessarily mean that the demand $D$ will decrease by $b$ unit exactly. So there exist some uncertainty in the movement of demand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, we observe movements in demand for energy drinks even without the change in price. If we are in a perfect deterministic world, this will not be case. But unfortunately(or fortunately) that is not the world we live in. This &lt;em&gt;randomness&lt;/em&gt; in demand is represented by this $u$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if we generalize this model
$$Y_i= β_1+β_2 X_{2i}+β_3 X_{3i}+⋯+β_k X_{ki}+u_i$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henceforth we will be calling $Y$ as endogenous or dependent variable and $X$’s as exogenous or explanatory variable. Also, $β$&#39;s are parameter for the model. Here, $i=1(1)n$ : number of observation and $k$ : number of parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the previous post, we are going to make certain assumptions about that ‘u’. These assumptions are very essential to build an econometric model to produce &lt;em&gt;best possible results&lt;/em&gt;. We will discuss later what we mean by  &lt;em&gt;best possible result&lt;/em&gt;.For now, lets focus on the assumptions-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt;. All the effects of excluded variables cancel each other  $$E(u_t )=0$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that those unobservable factors in our model has Zero effect &lt;strong&gt;on average&lt;/strong&gt;.  In other ways we can say that while there might be variations, on average those variations are Zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt;. The spread or variance of the error term is constant for all the values of $X$’s $$Var(u_t )=E(u_t^2 )=constant$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The variation in dependent variable (for our example demand) due to unobserved factors should stay same for any given value of dependent variables( price)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3&lt;/em&gt;. No association between error terms. $$E(u_t u_s )=0$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that the unobserved factors are not dependent on each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;4&lt;/em&gt;.Explanatory variables and the error terms are not also correlated.  $$E(X_{jt} u_s )=0$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No association for included and excluded variables. Or the unobserved factor does not affect the observed factor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;5&lt;/em&gt;. No exact linear relationship among $X$’s. Which means no perfect collinearity or no redundant variables. Which means the observed factors, or the independent factor should not be dependent on others !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;6&lt;/em&gt;. Error term is normally distributed. $$u_t \sim N(0, \sigma^2)$$Or we can say it is well behaved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;7&lt;/em&gt;. There shall be no specification bias or error. Or we can say the model is correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of these observation seems unrealistic. In real life two factors can be related to each other or past observations. Many of these assumptions does not work in real life, at least directly. Then, the question is why we should make these assumptions in the first place. The answers lie in our quest for aforementioned &lt;em&gt;best possible result&lt;/em&gt; or in this case &lt;em&gt;best possible estimation&lt;/em&gt; of the coefficient $\beta$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In next post we will discuss that how do we estimate these $\beta$.s and why that estimate should be the &lt;em&gt;best possible estimation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Econometric Model</title>
      <link>/post/econometric-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/econometric-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the field of data analysis, we often use regression models, especially linear regression to verify any hypothesis that we made about the data. Regression models uses different mathematical and statistical tools to analyze the data, find if there exist any pattern in the data, and some-times predicts from that data. Almost everyone, from business to science, use some form of data analysis to understand and analyze the problem in hand. In sciences we always see the usage of “curve fitting” to test any assumption from existing theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of economic sciences, the usage of data analysis has a special name. As a matter of fact, we call it “&lt;em&gt;Econometrics&lt;/em&gt;” mainly to sperate our selves for natural sciences. But is that so easy? Let us search a bit…&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word “&lt;em&gt;Econometrics&lt;/em&gt;” means “&lt;em&gt;the measurement in economics&lt;/em&gt;”  But this definition is too simple to digest. This definition is not complete either. Everything in economics is some sort of measurement. So, what is exactly “&lt;em&gt;Econometrics&lt;/em&gt;”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In plain and simple words econometrics is data analysis for economics but with a catch. Unlike natural sciences we not only use it to test theory and predict but also build models. So next time someone says “&lt;em&gt;whatever, it’s just same curve fitting&lt;/em&gt;” – no its not; we build theory with this! It means a lot to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, someone can ask we always used to build models (without even mathematical expression! We are artist!) so why do we need econometrics to build models? To understand this, we need to understand the difference between econometric models and economic model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now what is a model? Model is nothing but a simple but realistic representation of real-world phenomenon. We always prefer simple models over complex one because they are easier to understand. We assume something about the real world and based on those assumptions we build our models. With simple models there is always a fear of – either over-simplification of assumptions or making unrealistic assumption. Let us have an example-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say we want to measure the demand for monster energy drinks (not sponsored). We may start with assumption that demand of monster energy depends on the price of monster energy. Now based on this assumption we can write a model- If we denote demand for monster energy as D and Price of monster energy as P then we can write –&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$D = f(p)$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have a model. But one can say this model is oversimplified and unrealistic. Price of monster energy seldom changes and demand changes from age group. So, may be, we can include age and something else. That makes the model more complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we know what a model is. So, what is an economic model? Economic model is those set of assumptions that simplifies an economic behaviour. Say if we can write the above relation more clearly&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$D = a - bp$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is price is negatively related with the demand. So, this is an economic model. But we know there are some other factor which may also affect this demand for monsters. So, this is just an approximation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In econometric model we try to generalize this thing more. We include the other factors as “&lt;em&gt;disturbance&lt;/em&gt;”. Such as –&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$D=a-bP+u$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We assume certain feature about this disturbance later. First, we have one more problem to resolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While talking about models we always consider ‘&lt;em&gt;linear relation&lt;/em&gt;s’ in economics. But relations can not always be linear. Say this above relation can be –&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$D=\frac{a}{p^b} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we can always change this into a linear model –&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\ln p = \ln a - b\ln p$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, from now on when ever we consider any econometric model, we will only talk about linear model what we usually call – “&lt;em&gt;Linear Regression Model&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before finishing we should have a look into that “&lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;” term. As this is what separates an econometric model from an economic model. While economic models are definite econometric models are random mostly due to this “&lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;” . In the next post we will discuss more about this “&lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;” .&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
